Register of the Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty broadcast records
Hoover Institution Archives
Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty broadcast records
1951-2005
2000C120
Hoover Institution Archives
circa 7000 linear feet
American radio broadcasting organization operating Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty. Includes sound recordings of broadcasts, scripts, correspondence, and memoranda relating to broadcasts by Radio Free Europe to audiences in Eastern Europe and to broadcasts by Radio Liberty to audiences in the Soviet Union. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
RFE/RL, Inc.
Access
Collection is open for research. Portions of the collection stored off site. Portions of the collection in process open only by request. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Boxes 1 to 4556 are stored off-site. It may be possible to have a limited number of boxes brought to the archives reading room for examination. A minimum of two days notice is required. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for information.
Use copies of some sound recordings in the collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Other Institutions with Related Archival Materials
Access to RFE/RL Russian Service sound recordings is handled by the Vera and Donald Blinken Open Society Archives (OSA). They have a fully-searchable database available on their website at http://www.osaarchivum.org/digital-repository
Access to RFE/RL Polish Broadcasting Department sound recordings is handled by Polish Radio. They have a fully-searchable database available on their website at http://www.polskieradio.pl/68,Radia-Wolnosci
Access to Hungarian Broadcasting Department sound recordings is handled by the National Széchényi Library. The site Magyar Október, http://www.magyaroktober.hu/, provides access to programs broadcast by Radio Free Europe between October 22 and November 12, 1956.
Other institutions with collection materials related to RFE/RL include the following (click on the name of the institution for more information):
Bulgarian National Radio (Sofia, Bulgaria)
Czechslovak Documentation Centre (Prague, Czech Republic)
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library (New York, United States)
Film Archives, National Archives of Estonia (Tallinn, Estonia)
Inner Asian and Uralic National Resource Center (Bloomington, United States)
National Archives of Latvia (Riga, Latvia)
National Digital Archives (Warsaw, Poland)
National Széchényi Library (Budapest, Hungary)
Open Society Archives (Budapest, Hungary)
Shevchenko Scientific Society, Inc. (New York, United States)
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center of New Jersey (Somerset, United States)
Scope and Content of Collection
The RFE/RL Broadcast Archive consists of the materials produced by RFE/RL for its radio programs. While the primary elements of this collection are tapes and scripts, arranged by broadcast department or language service, there is also a good deal of derivative and associated documentation created, received, or collected in the course of the daily functioning of the broadcasting service. Such documentation includes editorial and research files, program logs and broadcast schedules, special programs, work plans, program lists, listener mail, papers of individual employees collected or produced in the course of their duties, and other types of documentation.
The most important set of such derivative documents is the Daily Broadcast Analyses (DBAs), which form the Daily Broadcast Analyses series. The DBAs were used by management and the broadcasting departments and language services to track the quality and content of programming. A special department, the Broadcasting Analysis Department, existed to collect data on programming and compile it into DBAs, which were then distributed to management and back to the appropriate desks. In the collection, they are arranged according to the category of origin: Radio Free Afghanistan, Radio Free Europe, Radio Free Europe Baltic, Radio Liberty Nationality Services, Radio Liberty Russian Service. The RFE DBAs contain texts of all the services and departments together for each day. DBAs were not issued every day, so the collection contains gaps. A separate category of translated scripts or parts of scripts is also part of the DBA series and listed at its end.
The Albanian Monitoring Subsection Records series consists of the papers of one of its employees, Nicolo Prenushi. An Albanian Language Service as such existed for a brief period of time in the early 1950s, leaving only the Monitoring Subsection thereafter.
The Azerbaijani Service Records series contains scripts and other materials, primarily collected writings and research files created by the service chief, Mirza Michaeli.
The Bulgarian, Czechslovak, Hungarian, Polish, Romanian, and Slovak Broadcast Departments and Services series contain similar material, arranged by physical form and chronologically thereafter, but it should be cited by date as the box numbers will change.
Many early scripts and programs are available only on microfilm. There is a register for these in a binder available in the Archives reading room, labeled "Programs on Microfilm," covering primarily the 1950s.
The News and Current Affairs Department Records series contains the news budget, which includes reports from wire agencies and other sources on events during the Hungarian Revolution of 1956 and Prague Spring of 1968, as well as certain other topics. The series also contains scripts – printed versions of news events and interviews as read by announcers – with sound bites of the event, speech, or interview on audio tapes.
The Sound Recordings series consists of broadcast recordings, monitoring recordings, off-air recordings, and music recordings. Broadcast recordings of RFE/RL broadcasts were captured either in the studio or direct from a transmitter. They constitute the defining record of what RFE/RL committed to air. Typical content includes news reports, interviews, speeches, sermons, dramatic programming, and music. Monitoring recordings represent radio broadcasts other than RFE/RL that were monitored on a radio in the RFE/RL office and recorded to tape. Off-air recordings are raw captures of interviews, speeches, literary readings, music performances, etc. that would have been edited for use on future broadcasts. Music recordings are predominantly commercially issued popular, classical, and folk releases collected for on-air play; they are sometimes called a service’s “music library.” It is important to note that music related broadcast programming, such as the Romanian Broadcasting Department’s “Metronome” program, are considered broadcast recordings since they contain whole programs as they were heard on air.
While part of the larger whole, each language service operated independently, with different practices regarding programming logs, the labeling of tapes, etc. Nearly all services reused tapes in an effort to conserve resources, particularly in the early years. Consequently, it is not uncommon for a language service to be missing sound recordings in multi-year spans, in some cases with significant gaps on the order of decades. Scripts are generally a more complete resource than recordings, which are usually scattered across time; scripts of early RFE programming are available on microfilm or paper even when no recordings may exist. Scripts are also available for many of the extant broadcast recordings and can serve as an index to their content. If an item of interest is found in a script, the date of that script can be used to search for a sound recording of the same date. This is the most convenient way to approach the recordings, as most have not been indexed for content. In some cases, as with the Polish service, a database can be used to find appropriate sound recordings.
From its earliest days through August 1995, when the radios adopted logging media to record all transmitters at once, nearly all recorded sound produced or recorded by RFE/RL was captured on ¼” open reel tape. Exceptions include an early set of Crusade for Freedom recordings on lacquer disc and particular services capturing limited broadcast runs, raw interview footage, and/or varying production elements on cassette and cartridge tape. Cassette, DAT and MiniDisc served this same purpose in the years following 1995.
From August 24, 1995 through October 31, 2006, Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty committed its broadcast recordings to multi-channel logging media. Recordings of programs broadcast August 24, 1995 through August 26, 1999 are saved on VHS tapes encoded using Racal Wordsafe machines while recordings broadcast September 25, 1999 through October 31, 2006 are on DDS tapes encoded using an RCS Tracker system. Both systems recorded multiple concurrent tracks of audio, capturing on one tape the content of several different transmitters. The Racal Wordsafe system captured twelve concurrent tracks, each 25 hours in duration, meaning each tape has the potential to hold 300 hours of content. Tape is not the only storage mechanism for audio recorded using the RCS Tracker system – it created audio files independent of tape, to be saved in whatever manner the user preferred – however tape (DDS in this case) was the method chosen by RFE/RL. Each tape contains upward of eight concurrent tracks; multiple decks operated simultaneously, affording the capture of all operating transmitters. The reader should note that, for inventory purposes, tapes from this period are counted as single physical items despite containing multiple recordings from different language services. Consequently, the sound recordings from this era – see the Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings series description – constitute 6,809 physical items rather than the 55,800 audio recordings.
Radio Free Europe.; Radio Liberty (Munich, Germany); Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Radio broadcasting--Soviet Union.; Audiotapes.
- Daily Broadcast Analyses, 1974-1993 (Boxes 1-264)
  Scope and Contents note
  Produced for internal review by RFE/RL's Broadcasting Analysis Department, DBAs are brief descriptions of the topics covered during each service and/or broadcasting department's broadcast day. Services/languages include: Armenian, Azerbaijani, Belarus, Bulgarian, Czechoslovak, Estonian, Georgian, Hungarian, Kazakh, Kyrgyz, Latvian, Lithuanian, Polish, Romanian, Russian, Slovak, Tajik, Tatar-Bashkir, Turkmen, Uigur (Uyghur) and Ukrainian. Arranged alphabetically by service and chronologically in semi-reverse order therein (reverse date frames in accordance with original order).
  Container List
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Daily Broadcast Analyses
- Afghan Service Sound Recordings, 2002-2004 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings. Target regions include Afghanistan. Languages include Dari and Pashto. Programming includes broadcast and other recordings. For Afghan content prior to 2002, see the Radio Free Afghanistan Records. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 2002-2006.
- Albanian Monitoring Subsection Records, 1952-1962 (Box 264)
  Papers of Nicolo Prennushi, employee of the Albanian Monitoring Subsection. See South Slavic Service (Balkan Service) Records for Albanian language RFE/RL broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Albanian Monitoring Subsection Records
- Armenian Service Records, 1989-1995 (Boxes 265-266)
  Sound recordings, newswires, and scripts. Target regions include Armenia. Languages include Armenian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Armenian Service Records
- Azerbaijani Service Records, 1934-1995 (Boxes 267-308)
  Sound recordings, daily format and work plans, editor's file, scripts, and special programs. Older papers (including scripts prior to 1992) are from the desk of Mecid Musazade; scripts and special programs, beginning from 1987, as received directly from RFE/RL. Also known as Radio Azadliq. Target regions include Azerbaijan. Languages include Azeri. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Azerbaijani Service Records
- Belarus Service Records, 1954-2007 (Boxes 309-332)
  Sound recordings, daily format and work plans, editor's file, letters from listeners, press monitoring, program logs, program reviews, scripts, special programs and telexes. Also known as Radio Svaboda. Target regions include Belarus. Languages include Belarusian/Belorussian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Belarus Service Records
- Bulgarian Broadcasting Department Records, 1968-2004 (Boxes 333-1026)
  Sound recordings, correspondents' reports, daily broadcast schedules, editor's file, letters from listeners, newscasts, newswires, program calendars, program logs, program summaries, schedules, scripts, special programs, and studio utilization reports. Target regions include Bulgaria. Languages include Bulgarian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Bulgarian Broadcasting Department
- Czech Service Records, 1993-2002 (Boxes 1027-1235)
  Sound recordings, scripts, special programs, and thumbnail sketches (with schedules). Target regions include Czech Republic. Languages include Czech. The Czechoslovak Broadcasting Department split into the Czech and Slovak services in 1993; for Czech language content prior to 1993, see Czechoslovak Broadcasting Department Records. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2002.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Czech Service Records
- Czechoslovak Broadcasting Department Records, 1947-1993 (Boxes 1236-2221)
  Sound recordings, editor's file, employee papers, index to tapes, letters from listeners, log sheets, production reports, program reviews, scripts, and special programs. Target regions include Czechoslovakia. Languages include Czech and Slovak. The Czechoslovak Broadcasting Department split into the Czech and Slovak services in 1993; for Czech and/or Slovak language content from after the split, see Czech Service Records and/or Slovak Service Records. See also Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Czechoslovak Broadcasting Department Records
- Estonian Service Records, 1940-2004 (Boxes 2222-2490)
  Sound recordings, clippings, correspondence, cover sheets, daily program summaries, editor's file, music programming, newswires, program reviews, scripts, Soviet media digest, special programs and tape index. Boxes 2488-2490 are out of numerical sequence. Target regions include Estonia. Languages include Estonian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2004 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Estonian Service Records
- Georgian Service Records, 1950-2004 (Boxes 2491-2595)
  Sound recordings, editor's file, printed matter, program reviews, scripts and special programs. Additional incremental materials in process. Also known as Ekho Kavkaza and Radio Tavisupleba. Target regions include Georgia and South Ossetia. Languages include Georgian and Russian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Georgian Service Records
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Georgian Service Records Oversize file
- Hungarian Broadcasting Department Records, 1951-1993 (Boxes 2596-3578)
  Sound recordings, correspondence, daily broadcast analyses, editor's file, employee papers, index to archival tapes, monitoring, news budget, program schedules, program summaries, scripts, special programs, thumbnail sketches and other document formats. Target regions include Hungary. Languages include Hungarian. See also Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Access to Hungarian Broadcasting Department sound recordings is handled by the National Széchényi Library. The site Magyar Október provides access to programs broadcast by Radio Free Europe between October 22 and November 12, 1956.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Hungarian Broadcasting Department Records
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Hungarian Broadcasting Department Records Oversize file
- Kazakh Service Records, 1953-2001 (Boxes 3579-3725)
  Sound recordings, daily format and work plans, editor's file, employee papers, monitoring, program logs, program reports, scripts, and special programs. Also known as Radio Azattyq. Target regions include Kazakhstan. Languages include Kazakh and Russian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Kazakh Service Records
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Kazakh Service Records Oversize file
- Kyrgyz Service Records, 1951-2014 (Boxes 3726-4076)
  Sound recordings, cover sheets, editor's files, faxes, program reviews, reports, scripts, and special programs. Also known as Radio Azattyk. Target regions include Kyrgyzstan. Languages include Kyrgyz. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Kyrgyz Service Records
- Latvian Service Records, 1939-2004 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings, cover sheets, editor's files, scripts, special programs, summaries of original scripts, tape index, and tentative programs. Target regions include Latvia. Languages include Latgalian and Latvian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2004 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Latvian Service Records
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Latvian Service Records Oversize file
- Lithuanian Service Records, 1975-2004 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings, cover sheets, editor's files, news reports, and scripts. Target regions include Lithuania. Languages include Lithuanian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2004 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Lithuanian Service Records,
- Moldovan Service Records, 1976-2013 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings and list of programs archived for the Web. Also known as Radio Europa Libera. Target regions include Moldova. Languages include Romanian and Russian. The Romanian Broadcasting Department began Moldova-specific programming in 1998 and ceased programming to Romania in 2008. For Romanian language content from 1959-2008, see the Romanian Broadcasting Department Records. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1998-2006.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Moldovan Service Records
- News and Current Affairs Department Records, 1956-1996 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings, newswires, summaries, and transcripts. In process. No specific target regions. Multiple languages, including English.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the News and Current Affairs Records
- North Caucasus Service Records, 1993-2013 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings, audience research and evaluation review, program logs, and program materials. Target regions include North Caucasus. Languages include Adyge, Avar, Chechen, Circassian, Ingush, Karachai-Balkar, Karakalpak, and Ossetian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the North Caucasus Service Records
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the North Caucasus Service Records Oversize file
- Pakistan Service Records, 2010-2013 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings. In process. Also known as Radio Marshaal. Target regions include northwestern Pakistan. Languages include Pashto. See also Radio Free Afghanistan Records for additional Pashto language content.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Pakistan Service Records
- Persian Service Records, 1998-2013 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings and clippings from Iranian newspapers. In process. Also known as Radio Farda. Target regions include Iran. Languages include Persian. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1998-2006.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Persian Service Records
- Polish Broadcasting Department Records, 1929-1997 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings, editor's files, and scripts. In process. Target regions include Poland. Languages include Polish. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Access to RFE/RL Polish Broadcasting Department sound recordings is handled by Polish Radio. They have a fully-searchable database available on their website at http://www.polskieradio.pl/68,Radia-Wolnosci
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Polish Broadcasting Department Records
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Polish Broadcasting Department Records Oversize file
- Radio Free Afghanistan Records, 1986-2013 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings. In process. Also known as Radio Azadi. Target regions include Afghanistan. Languages include Dari and Pashto. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1995-2006 and Daily Broadcast Analyses for brief descriptions of topics covered during broadcasts.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Radio Free Afghanistan Records
- Radio Free Iraq Records, 1998-2013 (On-shelf shelf)
  Sound recordings. In process. Target regions include Iraq. Languages include Arabic. See also Multiple Language Services Sound Recordings for recordings from 1998-2006.
  Downloadable PDF inventory of the Radio Free Iraq Records
- Romanian Broadcasting Department Records, 1959-1995 (On-shelf shelf)